Finding Aid for Kenneth C. Welch Papers 1915-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kenneth C. Welch Papers 1915-1972
Welch, Kenneth Curtis, 1891-1973.
Grand Rapids, Michigan, architect and planner. Correspondence, writings, working files, and photographs for out-of-state and Michigan projects, primarily in Grand Rapids, Lansing, Flint, and East Lansing; professional materials relating to problems of urban planning, the design of department stores and shopping centers, his general interest in lighting designs, traffic patterns, and parking areas, and to his work with the Lake Michigan Region Planning Committee, the American Institute of Architects and the Michigan Society of Architects; also Welch family materials, including record, 1915-1925, of the Welch Manufacturing Company of Grand Rapids, Michigan.
85520 Aa 2
13.6 linear feet in 15 boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Kenneth C. Welch (donor no. 5929 ) in 1976.
The collection is open for research.
Kenneth Curtis Welch, architect and planner, was born in Sparta, Michigan in 1891. In 1892, he and his family moved to Grand Rapids, where he remained throughout his life. Although Welch was educated as an architect, he spent only a small part of his career in the practice of conventional architecture. He studied briefly at the University of Michigan, but received both his B.S. and M.S. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1915 and 1916 respectively. Equipped with these degrees, he returned to Grand Rapids and began to practice his profession. In partnership with Charles Huggett, he designed twelve large traditional homes, many of which were never built because of World War I.
Confronted with a poor building market after the war, Welch went to work half-time for his father, as Vice-President in charge of planning of the Welch-Wilmarth Company. Welch's father Lyman, the inventor of the "Welch Folding Bed", had moved to Michigan from Vermont in order to manufacture his product. He later expanded into store fixtures and merged with the Wilmarth Show Case Company, also of Grand Rapids. The combined Welch-Wilmarth Company merged again in 1928 with the Grand Rapids Store Equipment Company and assumed that name. Welch served with this company as Vice-President in charge of Design until 1952 when he resigned to devote all of his time to shopping center development.
From his work with store fixtures, Welch learned the marketing and economic analysis skills which were to qualify him for his later work in shopping center planning and urban development. During the early years with his father's company, he also formulated many of his ideas about the relationships between human psychology and architecture. Welch believed that conventional architecture was flawed by self-imposed limitations. Architects were concerned only with visual aesthetics, and often neglected the essential environmental factors of illumination, ventilation and temperature and sound insulation.
Welch incorporated many of his architectural theories into the design of his own home, which was constructed in Grand Rapids in 1948. He heated the house by an early solar energy method which took maximum advantage of sun angles and reflections, and stored the sun's heat in specially constructed floor slabs. Elaborate lighting and sound controls and a forced ventilation system added to the concept of total environmental control. The house, however, was not a success and later became the library of the Kendall School of Design.
Welch's ideas about architecture and psychology were particularly applicable to store design. He wrote a series of articles about the effects of color, illumination and layout on consumer psychology and purchasing patterns. He also participated in a number of conferences on these issues, and throughout his career he was active with the American Institute of Architects and the American Institute of Planners.
Welch's most notable contribution to architecture was in the field of shopping center design and development. In 1953, in recognition of his work in this area, he was made a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Welch's first exposure to shopping centers was in 1929 when he designed the interior of a center in Ardmore, Pennsylvania. The Ardmore center was little more than an aggregate of stores; it lacked the unity of design and the regional orientation which characterized the post-World War II shopping centers.
The increased mobility allowed by the automobile radically altered shopping patterns in the United States. Welch recognized the changes early, and foresaw the replacement of small, cohesive neighborhood shopping areas by large, modern, regional shopping centers. One of the first such regional centers was Shoppers' World, built at Framingham, Massachusetts in 1948. As Vice-President of National Suburban Centers, Inc., the company responsible for Shoppers' World, Welch was instrumental in both the planning and the building of the center. The project received much attention from urban planners and architects. In 1963, Welch participated in a conference entitled "The Shopping Center as a Nucleus of Inter-City Activity" at the Harvard Graduate School of Architecture and Design, which used Shoppers' World as one of the models for study.
In the years following the building of Shoppers' World, Welch became one of the nation's leading consultants on shopping center design and planning. His best known works are Shoppers' World in Framingham, and the Mondawmin Center in Baltimore. In Michigan, he worked on Northland in Detroit, and Breton Village in Grand Rapids. Welch was an excellent amateur photographer and used photography--particularly aerial photography--to supplement his market studies and development plans.
As both architect and businessman, Welch was devoted to the concept of the regional shopping center. He believed that shopping centers only failed when the planners, the architects and the merchants involved failed to coordinate their efforts. He further thought that if a shopping center was to contribute to the prosperity of a city or region, it had to be planned and executed as part of the total business activity of the area. Welch's interest in shopping centers was thus closely related to his interest in urban and regional planning.
Welch first became involved in urban planning during World War II. From 1943 to 1948, he served as a member of Detroit's Civic Design Group, the precursor of Eliel Saarinen's Architects' Urban Design Collaborative. After the war, he worked on various urban and state-wide planning projects in Michigan.
Welch's most extensive planning activities were in his home city of Grand Rapids. In 1943, he and several other city residents organized the Grand Rapids City Planning Commission. He served as chairman of this group until 1952, and remained a member until his death. The group was actively involved in the planning of Grand Valley State College in 1960 and 1961, and developed the nationally acclaimed Grand Rapids Parking Plan. He later served as a member of the Kent County Planning Commission and the Lake Michigan Regional Planning Committee, and participated in the Great Lakes District Seminars of the American Institute of Architects.
Welch was always concerned over the role of government in urban planning and renewal. As an associate of the J. and G. Dauerman Architectural and Engineering Company of Grand Rapids, a position he assumed in 1952, Welch worked as a consultant on a series of projects for James W. Rouse, President of Community Research and Development, Inc. and later of the James W. Rouse Company. Rouse, a Baltimore businessman who shared Welch's interest in urban renewal, chaired the Mayor's Committee which developed the widely imitated Baltimore Plan for Slum Prevention, and served on President Eisenhower's Advisory Committee on Housing Policies and Programs. Welch's correspondence with Rouse, and with William Milliken and Gerald Ford, contains much information, from a developer's perspective, on the government's activity in housing and urban development during the 1950's and 1960's.
Kenneth Welch's combination of interests and his innovative techniques are perhaps particularly interesting in retrospect. He always refused to acknowledge architecture, planning and engineering as separate disciplines, and his accomplishments were consistently recognized in all three fields. In combining the traditional field of architecture with the contemporary practices of urban planning and market analysis, he was able to design shopping centers and city plans appropriate not to the past, but to the future.
The Welch papers include a small amount of biographical and personal material, but the bulk of the collection documents his work on architectural, design and planning projects in Michigan and across the country - many having to do with shopping malls, business districts and urban redevelopment. The collection is arranged in eight series: biographical materials; correspondence; personal, financial, and family materials; professional information files; Michigan project files; out-of-state project files; articles and speeches; and photographs.
Subjects:
American Institute of Architects.; Architects.; Architecture.; Automobile parking.; City planning--Michigan.; Department stores.; East Lansing (Mich.); Flint (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Lake Michigan Region Planning Council.; Lansing (Mich.); Michigan Society of Architects.; Shopping centers.; Welch family.; Welch Manufacturing Company (Grand Rapids, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Albuquerque (N.M.); Architecture.; Automobile parking.; Baltimore (Md.); Beverly (Mass.); Breton Village Shopping Center (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Business enterprises.; Business enterprises--Michigan--East Lansing.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Lansing.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Southfield.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Spring Lake.; Charlotte (N.C.); Church buildings--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Churches.; Denver (Colo.); Des Moines (Iowa); Detroit (Mich.)--Aerial photographs.; Edina (Minn.); El Paso (Tex.); Flint (Mich.)--Aerial photographs.; Fountain Street Baptist Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Framingham (Mass.); Glen Burnie (Md.); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Aerial photographs.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Italy.; Jacksonville (Fla.); Libraries--Michigan--Sparta.; New York (N.Y.); Northland Shopping Center (Southfield, Mich.); Owosso (Mich.)--Aerial photographs.; Parties--Michigan--East Lansing--1960.; Plainwell (Mich.); Saint Davids (Pa.); San Antonio (Tex.); Schools--Michigan--Whitehall.; Shopping.; Shopping centers.; Sparta (Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Wausau (Wis.); West Hartford (Conn.); Wilmington (N.C.)
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.
- Biographical materials
  Biographical is a small one folder accumulation of obituaries, letters about Welch, and a bibliography of his writings.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (1-1)
- Correspondence 1945-1972
  The correspondence series covers the period of 1945 to 1972 and is arranged alphabetically. The bulk of the correspondence concerns projects Welch was involved with and his professional activities. There are two folders of correspondence with Gerald Ford.
  - A (Box 1)
    (1-2)
  - American Institute of Architects (Box 1)
    (1-3)
  - American Institute of Planning Officials (Box 1)
    (1-4)
  - B (Box 1)
    (1-5; 1-6)
  - Bay City (Box 1)
    (1-7)
  - C, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-8; 1-9; 1-10)
  - Census Bureau (Box 1)
    (1-11)
  - Commerce Department (Box 1)
    (1-12)
  - Community Research and Development (Box 1)
    (1-13)
  - D, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-14; 1-15)
  - Dahme and Associates (Box 1)
    (1-16)
  - J. & G. Daverman Co. (Box 1)
    (1-17)
  - E (Box 1)
    (1-18)
  - Eno Foundation for Highway Traffic Control (Box 1)
    (1-19)
  - F (Box 1)
    (1-20)
  - Ford, Gerald R., 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-21; 1-22)
  - G (Box 1)
    (1-23)
  - General Electric, Nela Park (Box 1)
    (l-24)
  - H, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-25; 1-26)
  - J.L. Hudson Co. (Box 1)
    (1-27)
  - I (Box 1)
    (1-28)
  - Illuminating Engineering Society (Box 1)
    (1-29)
  - J (Box 1)
    (1-30)
  - K (Box 1)
    (1-31)
  - Kendall School of Design (Box 1)
    (1-32)
  - L (Box 1)
    (1-33)
  - M (Box 1)
    (1-34)
  - Michigan State Library (Box 1)
    (1-35)
  - Milliken, William G. (Box 1)
    (1-36)
  - Mc (Box 1)
    (1-37)
  - N (Box 1)
    (1-38)
  - National Suburban Centers, Inc. (Box 1)
    (1-39)
  - O (Box 1)
    (1-40)
  - P-4 (Box 1)
    (1-41)
  - Personal, 4 folders (Box 1)
    (1-42, etc. to 1-45)
  - R, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-46; 1-47)
  - James W. Rouse Co. (Box 1)
    (1-48)
  - S, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (2-1; 2-2)
  - Segoe, Ladislas (Box 2)
    (2-3)
  - Wilbur Smith Associates (Box 2)
    (2-4)
  - T-U (Box 2)
    (2-5)
  - V (Box 2)
    (2-6)
  - W, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (2-7; 2-8)
  - Ward, William G. (Box 2)
    (2-9)
  - Wiebe, John A. (Box 2)
    (2-10)
  - X-Y-Z (Box 2)
    (2-11)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2)
    (2-12)
- Personal, financial, and family
  The personal, financial, and family series, in addition to income tax and other financial papers includes material about the Welch family. There is also a record book, 1915-1925, of the Welch Manufacturing Company of Grand Rapids, Michigan and a scattering of files relating to the Grand Rapids Store Equipment Company.
  - Welch's election to the Jury of Fellows, A.I.A. 1952 (Box 2)
    (2-13)
  - Income tax papers
    - 1925-1935 (Box 2)
      (2-14)
    - 1936-1943 (Box 2)
      (2-15)
    - 1944-1950 (Box 2)
      (2-16)
  - Miscellaneous financial papers (Box 2)
    (2-17)
  - Papers concerning the Welch family history (Box 2)
    (2-18)
  - Record book of the Welch Manufacturing Company 1915-1925 (Box 2)
    (2-19)
  - Grand Rapids Store Equipment Company
    - Store Survey and Design Manual 1942 (Box 2)
      (2-20)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2)
      (2-21)
- Professional Information Files
  The professional information files relate to problems of urban planning, the design of department stores and shopping centers, his general interest in lighting designs, traffic patterns, and parking areas, and to Welch's work with the Lake Michigan Region Planning Committee, the American Institute of Architects and the Michigan Society of Architects.
  - Department Stores
    - Papers concerning store equipment development (Box 3)
      (3-1)
    - Papers concerning store modernization (Box 3)
      (3-2)
    - Store modernization show, New York City July 1947
      - Transcripts of clinic sessions (Box 3)
        (3-3)
      - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3)
        (3-4)
    - Store Histories (Box 3)
      (3-5)
    - Papers of the Branch Store Clinic, Research Bureau for Retail Training, University of Pittsburgh 1952 (Box 3)
      (3-6)
  - Shopping Centers
    - General information, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (3-7; 3-8)
    - Papers concerning downtown shopping areas (Box 3)
      (3-9)
    - Papers of the Harvard University Urban Design Conference, "The Shopping Center as a Nucleus of Inter-City Activity," 1963 (Box 3)
      (3-10)
    - Papers explaining Reilly's Law of Retail Gravitation (Box 3)
      (3-11)
  - Lighting
    - General Information (Box 3)
      (3-12)
    - Printed materials (Box 3)
      (3-13)
    - Papers of the A.I.A. School Lighting Roundtable 1946 (Box 3)
      (3-14)
    - Illuminating Engineering Society Project on School Lighting 1946-1949
      - Reports (Box 3)
        (3-15)
      - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3)
        (3-16)
    - Papers of the A.I.A. Symposium on Light and Illumination 1950 (Box 3)
      (3-17)
    - Papers of the Inter-Society Color Council 1949-1952
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
        (3-18)
      - Reports and newsletters (Box 3)
        (3-19)
  - Traffic and Parking
    - General Information, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (3-20; 3-21)
    - Parking Angle Studies (Box 3)
      (3-22)
    - Roundtable on Urban Traffic (Box 3)
      (3-23)
    - Papers of the Highway Research Board 1918-1950 (Box 3)
      (3-24)
    - Data on Highway Interchanges (Box 3)
      (3-25)
  - Urban Planning
    - General information (Box 3)
      (3-26)
    - Papers of the A.I.A. Committee on Community Planning 1958 (Box 3)
      (3-27)
    - Papers concerning the Baltimore Plan for 'Public and Private Housing 1949 (Box 3)
      (3-28)
- Michigan Projects
  Projects on which Welch worked have been separated into two series arranged alphabetically by geographic location. These series are Michigan project files and Out-of-state project files. The Michigan project files are strongest for Grand Rapids, Lansing, Flint, and East Lansing.
  - Allendale: Grand Valley College
    - Correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 3)
      (3-29)
    - Reports and proposals 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (3-30; 3-31)
    - News clippings 1960-1961 (Box 3)
      (3-32)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3)
      (3-33)
    - Building plans (Box 3)
      (3-34)
  - Detroit
    - Economic studies (Box 3)
      (3-35)
    - City Master plans 1945-1947 (Box 3)
      (3-36)
    - Printed materials 1941-1960 (Box 4)
      (4-l)
    - Parking plans 1945-1947 (Box 4)
      (4-2)
    - Northland Shopping Center
      - Miscellaneous papers 1946 (Box 4)
        (4-3)
  - East Lansing: Central Business District Study
    - Correspondence 1954-1964 (Box 4)
      (4-4)
    - Economic Surveys (Box 4)
      (4-5)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 4)
      (4-6)
  - Flint: Central Business District Study
    - Correspondence 1960 (Box 4)
      (4-7)
    - Economic study and Market Analysis (Box 4)
      (4-8)
    - Reports of the Flint Planning Commission 1959, 3 folders (Box 4)
      (4-9; 4-10; 4-11)
  - Grand Rapids
    - Buildings
      - Central Reformed Church--Lighting Design
        - Correspondence and Plans 1964-1969 (Box 4)
          (4-12)
      - Fountain Street Church-Lighting Design
        - Plans (Box 4)
          (4-13)
        - Correspondence 1965-1967 (Box 4)
          (4-14)
        - Correspondence 1968 (Box 4)
          (4-15)
        - Miscellaneous papers (Box 4)
          (4-16)
      - Church of the Nazarene
        - Correspondence 1960-1965 (Box 4)
          (4-17)
        - Plans and specifications (Box 4)
          (4-18)
      - Mt. Mercy Academy Chapel-Lighting Design (Box 4)
        (4-19)
      - Westgate Methodist Church
        - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 4)
          (4-20)
        - Building specifications (Box 4)
          (4-21)
        - Architectural plans (Box 4)
          (4-22)
      - Reed's Lake Apartments
        - Papers concerning zoning controversy 1967-1968 (Box 4)
          (4-23)
      - Breton Village Shopping Center
        - Correspondence 1955-1958 (Box 4)
          (4-24)
        - Correspondence 1968-1970 (Box 4)
          (4-25)
        - Economic studies (Box 4)
          (4-26)
        - Architectural plans (Box 4)
          (4-27)
        - Miscellaneous papers (Box 4)
          (4-28)
      - Kenneth C. Welch Residence
        - Correspondence 1944-1949 (Box 4)
          (4-29)
        - Architectural plans and sketches, 2 folders (Box 4)
          (4-30; 4-31)
        - Sun angle and temperature studies for solar heating (Box 4)
          (4-32)
        - Articles (Box 4)
          (4-33)
      - Kent Country Club
        - Architectural specifications (Box 5)
          (5-1)
        - Correspondence (Box 5)
          (5-2)
      - Craig Hecker Residence
        - Miscellaneous papers 1966-1967 (Box 5)
          (5-3)
    - Planning
      - Grand Rapids City Planning Commission
        - Economic Development Data (Box 5)
          (5-4)
        - Minutes and Memos January-June 1947 (Box 5)
          (5-5)
        - Minutes and Memos July 1947-January 1948 (Box 5)
          (5-6)
        - Correspondence 1947 (Box 5)
          (5-7)
        - News clippings 1956-1970 (Box 5)
          (5-8)
        - Zoning regulations 1940-1952 (Box 5)
          (5-9)
        - Century-Monroe Expressway Project 1948-1949 (Box 5)
          (5-10)
      - Grand Rapids Downtown Urban Renewal Project
        - Reports 1962-1969 (Box 5)
          (5-11)
        - "Short Range Development Plan and Financing Proposals Central Business District, Grand Rapids, Michigan" Report to the Renewal Committee (Box 5)
          (5-12)
        - Correspondence January 1967-March 1970 (Box 5)
          (5-13)
        - Correspondence April 1970-August 1972 (Box 5)
          (5-14)
        - Miscellaneous papers (Box 5)
          (5-15)
      - Grand Rapids Civic Design Committee
        - Miscellaneous papers 1948-1949 (Box 5)
          (5-16)
      - Grand Rapids Parking Plan
        - Correspondence 1945-1954 (Box 5)
          (5-17)
        - Reports 1947, 2 folders (Box 5)
          (5-18; 5-19)
        - Parking Structure plans (Box 5)
          (5-20)
        - Articles and News clippings 1945-1948 (Box 5)
          (5-21)
      - Grand Rapids Historical Society
        - Miscellaneous papers 1971-1972 (Box 5)
          (5-22)
      - Miscellaneous Printed materials concerning Grand Rapids Urban Planning 1942-1952 (Box 5)
        (5-23)
      - Kent County Planning Commission
        - Minutes 1963-1970 (Box 5)
          (5-24)
        - Minutes 1971-1973 (Box 5)
          (5-25)
        - Correspondence 1962-1972 (Box 5)
          (5-26)
        - Reports 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
          (5-27; 5-28)
        - Papers concerning the Kent County Airport Cascade Zoning Ordinance 1962-1963 (Box 5)
          (5-29)
        - Miscellaneous papers (Box 5)
          (5-30)
      - Printed Reports concerning Grand Rapids urban development (Box 6)
  - Kalamazoo
    - Downtown Development Studies 1959 (Box 7)
      (7-1)
  - Lansing
    - Downtown Rehabilitation Program 1957-1961
      - Correspondence
        - December 1957-June 1958 (Box 7)
          (7-2)
        - July-December 1958 (Box 7)
          (7-3)
        - January-April 1959 (Box 7)
          (7-4)
        - May-December 1959 (Box 7)
          (7-5)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
          (7-6)
      - News clippings
        - 1958 (Box 7)
          (7-7)
        - January-June 1959 (Box 7)
          (7-8)
        - July-December 1959 (Box 7)
          (7-9)
        - 1960 (Box 7)
          (7-10)
      - Economic Studies (Box 7)
        (7-11)
      - Miscellaneous papers (Box 7)
        (7-12)
      - Printed reports, 4 folders (Box 7)
        (7-13, etc. to 7-16)
      - Tape recording of K.C. Welch's presentation to the Lansing Downtown Redevelopment Council (Box 7)
        (7-17)
    - Capitol Shopping Mall
      - Miscellaneous papers 1966 (Box 7)
        (7-18)
  - Midland
    - Central Business District Development Report 1945 (Box 7)
      (7-19)
  - Mt. Clemens
    - Papers concerning urban development 1958-1960 (Box 7)
      (7-20)
  - Muskegon
    - Papers concerning central business district redevelopment (Box 7)
      (7-21)
  - Owosso
    - Market study for the J.A. Byerly Co. (Box 7)
      (7-22)
  - Plainwell
    - Correspondence concerning expansion of the public library 1964-1965 (Box 7)
      (7-23)
  - Pontiac
    - Report on Urban Planning 1958 (Box 7)
      (7-24)
  - Sparta: Public Library Expansion Project
    - Correspondence 1959-1971 (Box 7)
      (7-25)
    - Building plans (Box 7)
      (7-26)
  - Spring Lake
    - Papers concerning community planning (Box 7)
      (7-27)
  - St. John's
    - Development plan 1970 (Box 7)
      (7-28)
  - Wayne: Downtown Redevelopment Project
    - Reports 1960-1964 (Box 8)
      (8-1)
    - Correspondence 1964 (Box 8)
      (8-2)
  - Isabella County
    - Planning Guide 1969 (Box 8)
      (8-3)
  - Michigan Planning and Development